Well, this was unexpected. In fact, the
only thing that forecast we were on a
weakening trend for labor market data
was this report I broke through about 2
and 1/2 weeks ago. This was the chart of
ADP data, the ADP weekly employment
data, where I referred to how crap it
had been during the first year under
Trump. This is just sort of a trend that
had been going. That doesn't necessarily
have to do with Trump, though it in part
could because we also had liberation
day, right? So, ADP was pretty crap and
weak towards the end of last year. A lot
of uncertainty and an overall slowing
economy. So, it could be both. Then, we
had this boom over here in the
beginning, especially after IEEPA died
in this pre-hormuz relaxation,
sort of like the pre-hormuz,
you know, collapse of ceasefire. And
then now we have this new ceasefire,
right? Like at that moment, we started
really seeing hiring again. Okay, IEEPA
tariffs dead. Here's a hiring window.
Let's get ahead of price increases.
Okay, there's a ceasefire. Prices are
still going to jump a little bit. Let's
get ahead of some of that. Let's get
some production cooking. Let's see where
we stabilize, right? So, we get a surge
in ADP hiring that goes up to about
40,000 or so. And and this plummets,
you know, on a trend line. I drew this
sort of teal trend line here and
plummets down to around,
you know, 15,000 or so. The last ADP
report came in suggesting that this
plummeting has actually fallen even
more. That plummeting now brings this
down to 10,000 right here where my mouse
says. That's because that last ADP jobs
report came in at 40,000.
And that's not good, right? So, where do
we sit today? Well, today we ended up
getting the jobs report of the BLS uh
jobs data. We had a survey of 80,000, we
actually got negative 23,000.
Now, this basically kills the idea for a
rate hike for now. Now, still have data
to go. Like we said yesterday, we got to
get through two more CPI sets of data,
another jobs report. Who knows? Maybe
something's weird about this jobs
report. But,
I have a
little bit of a conclusion for it. We'll
get to We'll We'll keep it short. We'll
get to it. Uh but, let's get through
some more of this data and try to
understand what's going on. So, the
prior
uh employment report was revised down by
57,000.
So, what we thought was a 77,000 report
actually turned out to be a 20,000
report. And the two-month revision is
now a negative 103,000.
Private payrolls also missed, coming in
at just 30k versus the 82k survey.
Not good. Prior was also revised down
from 49 to 30k.
Average hourly earnings came in at just
0.1%.
Keep that in your mind. That's actually
a really important point we're going to
talk about in just a moment as to, you
know, what what is potentially Like,
what does that even mean, Kevin? We'll
explain. Uh year-over-year um
uh average hourly earnings came in at
3.2 versus 3.5 expected. Unemployment
rate actually fell, but again, only
because the participation rate fell as
the household survey says we are now
down 87,000 people in the workplace and
178 uh thousand job seekers down. And
you can actually see some of this in the
uh BLS language as well, which I don't
know. Sometimes I read it and I'm like,
man, this just sounds like BS language.
It doesn't sound like Bureau of Labor
Statistics. It sounds like some bull.
Uh
>> [clears throat]
>> and I I think the the frustration that I
have with it is that as people say they
are no longer interested in working,
right? We've got this
you know, what do we have here right
here?
Uh the number of people employed
part-time for economic reasons, 4.8
million. That's a lot of people, we know
that. Uh but right here, the number of
people not in the labor force who want a
job, little changed at 5.9 million.
That's that's a lot. It's a big level.
These individuals were not counted
because they were not actively looking
for a job or were unable to take a job
in the last 4 weeks. Okay, we know this
has been a number that people refer to,
you know, they have the different
versions like, oh, well, look at the U6
unemployment rate, right? Which accounts
for these people. That's fine.
We don't want to get uh you know, up in
a dizzy about month-over-month numbers.
What frustrates me is that this number
right here,
the labor force participation rate keeps
going down.
And there's a reason it keeps going
down. Uh the labor force participation
rate you can see
right here on the household survey. You
can see since last year, since July of
2025, it's come down 1.1%
which is actually quite a bit for a
participation rate because if you've got
150 million workers, you know, a
difference of 1% is like 1 and 1/2
people 1 and 1/2 million people not
working, right?
But there's something greater going on
and I think what it is
is
Well, obviously people aren't using the
coupon to be Kevin. OH, NO.
YEAH, I'M GOING TO say it's totally a
joke. It's a bad joke, Kevin. Jokes are
meant to be funny. You really get the
bat out. No.
Uh people are losing their peepee.
Workers for some reason, and I think we
all can surmise the reason, have no
pricing power anymore.
Average hourly earnings up just 0.1% on
the month is not pricing power. Humans
are competing with the robots. Yeah, AI.
Okay.
That also helps us explain this. As fun
as it is for people who don't like
Donald Trump to
basically blame the fall in the
participation rate on Trump's
immigration policies or
uh the feelings that they get that
everything is corrupt when for the first
time ever you give the give a president
an immunity and then then they they
basically turn into insider traders and
show us how bad the suits on Wall Street
can be.
Uh you know, some people might have
those beliefs
and that might discourage people. And
they'll you know what, F it. I'm going
to retire. I'm done. You know, people
fortunate enough to be able to retire,
right?
Uh some people would blame that. Other
people say, "No, you know, it's
it doesn't actually have to do with any
of that. It has to do with artificial
intelligence." And this this like
precipitous plummet, which you know, it
doesn't even look that precipitous
when you zoom in on it, but I mean, look
at history here. It's really rare that
you see I mean, you saw it in COVID,
obviously, but it's really rare that you
see these like tanks.
This is starting to tank vertically like
what we saw almost during COVID. Here,
let's zoom in a little bit more. Let's
go to the last 5 years.
It's you know, this is COVID recovery
over here, slowly coming out of it.
We're starting to take the elevator down
in participation.
And with average hourly earnings up 0.1%
I personally think there's
glaring evidence that artificial
intelligence at the moment is killing
more jobs than it's creating.
Everybody's got their anecdotes. I've
got my anecdotes, too. Workers in the
office, don't need you. Workers on AI,
we're hiring them, BABY. MORE AI. Our
reinvest AI product is cooking. We keep
adding more and more, right? I mean, you
can see that at househack.com Uh what
what what our AI our housing AI product
is. And I think it's really freaking
good. We even get a little demo over
here. Uh and and it's you know, it's
really early in our beta phase.
But here's the thing. Something that
people haven't been talking about. And I
honestly, I don't know why CNBC didn't
air this. But
CNBC aired this on TV, but they didn't
end up putting it on their YouTube
channel. And I was really disappointed
by this. They cut it out, which I was
I thought was very strange. If you type
in Wells Fargo CNBC, you end up getting
this short video from 2 days ago that's
only 4 minutes long. And it's we're
focused on growing revenues and returns.
Okay.
They literally cut out the segment where
he said, "We're going to be displacing a
lot of workers due to artificial
intelligence.
We are becoming more efficient. That's
how we're going to grow revenues." They
cut that part out probably cuz it just
doesn't sound good, right? People going
to be like, "Man, F U Wells." Right?
But But he was saying the quiet part out
loud. And he actually acknowledged he's
like, "There's probably going to be a
gap. There's going to be a gap between
what you know, when people are hired to
replace all these people. And it's not
sure that
uh you know, people catching up with
skills
is even going to be enough. Because even
if everybody somehow catches up with the
skills they need, there still might not
be enough jobs." And I actually thought
I was like, "Damn, that's that's
depressing." Now, at the same time he
was like, "Oh, but everybody's still
spending. The consumer's good, you know,
corporates are doing great. Everything's
great." But really what this means for
the long term. And And I think this is
uh sort of the bottom line of this labor
report. What this really means for the
long term is
this is
a a warning that we are likely in the
late
innings. Not like the Ray Dalio
government debt cycle late innings.
Okay, that is a baseball game that plays
out over hundreds of years. The collapse
of the dollar, the collapse of credit,
you know, the government credit cycles,
that takes a very long time.
I'm talking about the AI cycle. I'm
talking about the next like three to
five.
Probably late cycle. Increases our
downside risk and should make us more
conservative. It doesn't mean, you know,
oh, you know, don't invest. It just
means there's even more reiteration to
just be careful on debt exposure. Now,
keep in mind, this does now lower the
risk Federal Reserve is going to hike.
Uh but the 10-year Treasury, even though
it's down five basis points, it's still
above 4.6.
It still sucks. You know, Brent is still
above $81. So, this isn't great. Uh I
think overall this is bad news and it
increases longer-term risks and
hopefully this is just like
>> [snorts]
>> a blip, but honestly, it's starting to
look more and more, especially with the
ADP trend, that the real blip was the
hiring boom after the ceasefire.
That that was a temporary rush of
hiring. Uh you know, and and
some with some limited effect because of
FIFA.
Uh you know, we looked specifically at
some of the data in the last uh
labor report and we found it seemed to
be relatively limited, the impact for
leisure and hospitality. In fact, those
were the sectors that
uh you know, have have lost quite a bit,
which again, it makes you you think
like, "Okay, but that's, you know,
afterwards." We would expect to see some
layoffs after uh the FIFA event in
leisure and hospitality, but the the
real issue is we're seeing less hiring
in areas that we usually see them.
Certainly government. Government is
firing. Uh you but you've also got
health care that's uh hiring a lot less
than usual, way way below trend. ADP
acknowledged this as well. And some of
these things are weird just for this
time of the year. So, uh you know, even
retail trade down -19 here. Now, that's
the government data, but the ADP data
earlier this week wasn't super strong
either, and the trend is weakening. So,
again, this isn't run for cover, it's
the trend is weakening.
Know that as this weakens, [music]
one day SHY is going to hit the fan.
This is your loudest warning sign
that that you know
whether it's AI or something.
The jobs are going out the back door,
and a lot of people aren't paying
attention to it right now. And uh
when when the unemployment rate starts
going up, the market's going to start
panicking about a recession.
>> Why not advertise these things that you
told us here? I feel like nobody else
knows about this.
>> We'll We'll try a little advertising and
see how it goes.
>> Congratulations, man. You have done so
much. People love you. People look up to
you.
>> Kevin Paffrath, a financial analyst and
YouTuber, Meet Kevin. Always great to
get your take.
>> [music]